[
  {
    "question": "Welcome to Eironauts! What is our mission?",
    "incorrect_answers": ["To defeat enemies"],
    "correct_answer": "To tackle air pollution through knowledge and action",
    "explanation": "As an Eironaut, your mission is to tackle air pollution by increasing your knowledge on the topic of air pollution and taking informed actions.",
    "link": ""
  },
  {
    "question": "What happens after completing the quiz?",
    "incorrect_answers": ["You win a prize", "The game ends"],
    "correct_answer": "You embark on an adventure",
    "explanation": "After the quiz, if you get a high enough score (10/15), you'll start an adventure influenced by real-time news articles. Your decisions will impact the future of your community.",
    "link": ""
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the main goal of Eironauts?",
    "incorrect_answers": [
      "To sell in-game items",
      "To reach the highest level",
      "To defeat the final boss"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "To empower players to learn about the risks and solutions association with air pollution",
    "explanation": "Eironauts aims to empower players to take action against air pollution by providing knowledge and tools to make informed decisions.",
    "link": ""
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following forms of pollution poses the highest risks for poor health or mortality?",
    "incorrect_answers": ["Soil", "Water", "Noise"],
    "correct_answer": "Air",
    "explanation": "Outdoor air pollution from industrial activities, vehicles, and burning biomass, along with indoor pollution from the use of solid fuels for cooking and heating, contribute to a wide range of health issues. These include respiratory infections, heart disease, stroke, and lung cancer. Despite the risks posed by soil and water pollution through substances like heavy metals and pathogens, air pollution's extensive impact on various health outcomes marks it as the most significant environmental threat to human health.",
    "link": "https://www.who.int/health-topics/air-pollution#tab=tab_1"
  },
  {
    "question": "What percentage of people breathe polluted air worldwide?",
    "incorrect_answers": ["95%", "85%", "75%"],
    "correct_answer": "99%",
    "explanation": "99% of the world's population breathes air that exceeds WHO guideline limits containing high levels of pollutants.",
    "link": "https://www.who.int/health-topics/air-pollution#tab=tab_1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following day-to-day activities contribute the most to air pollution in Ireland, especially during wintertime?",
    "incorrect_answers": [
      "Travelling short distances by motor engine car",
      "Engine idling when parked outside schools, hospitals or other buildings",
      "Burning solid fuel (coal, turf, wood) for home heating"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "All of these options",
    "explanation": "The Environmental Protection Agency reports and data have shown that dependence of fossil fuels for travel and burning of solid fuel for home heating are key drivers of air pollution in Ireland, which is similar to other countries in Europe and globally.‚Äù Source: EPA Air quality in Ireland 2022",
    "link": "https://www.epa.ie/publications/monitoring--assessment/air/air-quality-in-ireland-2022.php"
  },
  {
    "question": "Particulate Matter (also called PM) is a particle (solid) air pollutant mainly produced by solid fuel burning. PM particles are very small. How many times smaller than a human hair is PM?",
    "incorrect_answers": ["1 times smaller", "100 times smaller"],
    "correct_answer": "5 times smaller and 20 times smaller",
    "explanation": "The size of PM depends on the width of the particle, which is measured in microns (1 metre = 1 million microns). A human hair is around 50-70 microns in width. PM10 (particles up to 10 micrometers) which includes dust, pollen, and mold, and PM2.5 (particles up to 2.5 micrometers), produced from combustion processes.",
    "link": "https://www.epa.gov/pm-pollution/particulate-matter-pm-basics "
  },
  {
    "question": "Which pollutant can penetrate our body's protective barriers to cause damage to our lungs, heart, and brain?",
    "incorrect_answers": ["PM10", "CO2", "NOx"],
    "correct_answer": "PM2.5",
    "explanation": "PM2.5 is particularly hazardous as it can penetrate deep into the lungs and bloodstream, leading to respiratory and cardiovascular issues, and with long-term exposure, chronic diseases such as asthma and heart disease.",
    "link": "https://www.epa.gov/pm-pollution/particulate-matter-pm-basics"
  },

  {
    "question": "Nitrogen dioxide (NO2) is a poisonous gas that can cause asthma, respiratory infections, and even poor cognitive health. Which of the following actions is the most effective to reduce NO2 levels and protect health?",
    "incorrect_answers": [
      "Supporting better building energy efficiency through home retrofits",
      "Wearing masks when the air quality is poor"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Reducing the use of motor cars for short journeys in our cities and Avoiding engine idling when parked outside buildings",
    "explanation": "Reducing the use of motor cars and avoiding engine idling are two key actions to limit levels of NO2, as this is mainly caused by car fumes and emissions. Home retrofits are very important to make homes warmer and rely less on solid fuel burning for home heating. Wearing masks is a good way to protect yourself from dirty air, but it does not help to reduce air pollution.",
    "link": "https://www.epa.ie/our-services/monitoring--assessment/assessment/irelands-environment/air/ "
  },

  {
    "question": "Why are plants and green spaces important for clean air?",
    "incorrect_answers": [
      "They lower the ground temperature and keep the air cool",
      "They use solar energy to grow",
      "They increase biodiversity"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "They absorb and trap pollutants from the surrounding air",
    "explanation": "Plants absorb and digest gas pollutants such as NO2 as a nutrient. Solid pollutants such as PM stick to the tree leaves and trunk and are then washed away by rain. The other options are all true about plants, although they contribute less (or not at all) to keep the air clean.",
    "link": "https://earth.org/unveiling-plants-hidden-air-quality-role/"
  },
  {
    "question": "Air pollution affects everyone's health equally",
    "incorrect_answers": [
      "True",
      "It only affects people with pre-existing conditions",
      "It only affects outdoor workers"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "False",
    "explanation": "While air pollution is harmful to everyone, children, older people, and pregnant women are more susceptible to air pollution-related diseases.",
    "link": "https://www.who.int/news-room/spotlight/how-air-pollution-is-destroying-our-health"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of particulate matter is one of the largest contributors to global warming?",
    "incorrect_answers": ["Carbon dioxide", "Methane", "Sulfur dioxide"],
    "correct_answer": "Black carbon",
    "explanation": "Black carbon, a component of fine particulate matter, is one of the largest contributors to global warming. It is produced through the incomplete combustion of fossil fuels, biofuels, and biomass, with primary sources including diesel engines, cookstoves, wood burning, and forest fires.",
    "link": "https://www.ccacoalition.org/short-lived-climate-pollutants/black-carbon"
  },
  {
    "question": "Have any communities in Ireland developed a clean air strategy?",
    "incorrect_answers": [
      "No communities have developed one",
      "Multiple communities have developed one",
      "It is under development in all communities"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Cork City is the only local authority to have a clean air strategy",
    "explanation": "Cork City is the only local authority to have developed a clean air strategy, providing a policy framework for promoting clean air.",
    "link": "https://www.corkcity.ie/en/council-services/services/environment/air-quality/air-quality-strategy.html"
  },
  {
    "question": "What health diseases can we prevent by reducing air pollution in our communities?",
    "incorrect_answers": [
      "Respiratory diseases",
      "Heart diseases and cancer",
      "Neurological and mental disorders"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "All of these options",
    "explanation": "Air pollution is the single largest environmental health risk in Europe and other parts of the world. It can affect multiple health issues and contribute to premature mortality. Taking actions that reduce air pollution, no matter how big or small, is important to promote health and wellbeing in our communities.",
    "link": "https://www.eea.europa.eu/en/topics/in-depth/air-pollution/eow-it-affects-our-health "
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the estimated range of annual global deaths attributed to air pollution from all sources?",
    "incorrect_answers": [
      "7000 to 9000",
      "70,000 to 90,000",
      "700,000 to 900,000"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "7 to 9 million",
    "explanation": "The estimated range of annual deaths attributed to air pollution from all sources spans from 6.7 million to 8.8 million, according to various studies. The World Health Organization (WHO) estimates 7 million deaths per year, with 4.2 million from outdoor pollution and 3.8 million from indoor pollution. The Institute for Health Metrics and Evaluation (IHME) estimates 6.7 million deaths, with 4.5 million from outdoor pollution and 2.3 million from indoor pollution. Lelieveld et al. (2019) provides a higher estimate of 8.8 million deaths from all sources of air pollution, including 5.5 million from anthropogenic sources and 3.6 million from burning fossil fuels. Another study by Lelieveld et al. (2015) estimates 3.3 million deaths due to outdoor air pollution. Vohra et al. (2021) estimate 8.7 million deaths due to air pollution from burning fossil fuels alone.",

    "link": "https://ourworldindata.org/data-review-air-pollution-deaths"
  }
]
